Time Warner Audio books presents
Rich Dad Poor Dad, written by Robert
Kiyosaki with Sharon l Lecter, CPA,
and read by Steven Hoy, featuring
an introduction by Robert Kiyosaki.
I had two fathers, a
rich one, and a poor one.
One was highly educated and intelligent.
He had a PhD and completed four years of
undergraduate work in less than two years.
The other father never
finished the eighth grade.
Both men were successful in
their careers, working hard.
All their lives, both earned
substantial incomes, yet one
struggled financially all his life.
The other would become one of the
richest men in Hawaii, one guy leaving
tens of millions of dollars to his
family charities and his church.
The other left bills will be paid.
Both men were strong,
charismatic, and influential.
Both men offered me advice, but
they did not advise the same things.
Both men believed strongly in
education, but did not recommend
the same course of study.
If I had had only one dad, I would've
had to accept or reject his advice.
Having two dads advising me offered me
the choice of contrasting points of view,
one of a rich man and one of a poor man.
Instead of simply accepting or
rejecting one or the other, I found
myself thinking more, comparing
and then choosing for myself.
The problem was the rich man was not
rich yet, and the poor man, not yet poor.
Both were just starting out on their
careers and both were struggling
with money and families, but
they had very different points of
view about the subject of money.
For example, one dad would say.
The love of money is the root of all evil.
The other, the lack of money
is the root of all evil.
As a young boy, having two strong fathers
both influencing me was difficult.
I wanted to be a good son and
listen, but the two fathers
did not say the same things.
The contrast in their points of
view, particularly where money
was concerned, was so extreme
that I grew curious and intrigued.
I began to start thinking for long periods
of time about what each was saying.
Much of my private time was spent
reflecting, asking myself questions
such as, why does he say that?
And then asking the same question
of the other dad's statement,
it would've been much easier to
simply say, yeah, he's right.
I agree with that.
Or to simply reject the point of
view by saying the old man doesn't
know what he's talking about.
Instead having two dads whom my love
forced me to think and ultimately
choose a way of thinking for myself as
a process, choosing to think for myself
turned out to be much more valuable in
the long run rather than simply accepting
or rejecting a single point of view.
One of the reasons the rich get richer,
the poor get poor, and the middle class
struggles in debt is because a subject of
money is taught at home, not in school.
Most of us learn about
money from our parents.
So what can a poor parent
tell their child about money?
They simply say, stay in
school and study hard.
The child may graduate with excellent
grades, but with a poor person's
financial programming and mindset.
It was learned while the child was young.
Money is not taught in schools.
Schools focus on scholastic
and professional skills,
but not financial skills.
This explains how smart bankers,
doctors, and accountants who are in
excellent grades in school may still
struggle financially all their lives.
Our staggering national debt is due
in large part to highly educated
politicians and government officials
making financial decisions with little
or no training on the subject of money.
I often look ahead to a new millennium
and wonder what will happen when we
have millions of people who will need
financial and medical assistance.
They'll be dependent upon their families
or the government for financial support.
What will happen with Medicare and
social security run out of money?
How will a nation survive if teaching
children about money continues
to be left to parents, most of
whom will be or already are poor?
Because I had two influential
fathers, I learned from both of them.
I had to think about each dad's advice,
and in doing so, I gained valuable
insight into the power and effect
of one's thoughts on one's life.
For example, one dad had a habit
of saying, I can't afford it.
The other dad forbade
those words to be used.
He insisted.
I say, how can I afford it?
One is a statement and
the other is a question.
One lets you off the hook and
the other forces you to think.
My soon to be a rich dad would
explain that by automatically
saying the words, I can't afford it.
Your brain stops working by asking
the question, how can I afford it?
Your brain is put to work.
He did not mean by everything you wanted.
He was fanatical about
exercising your mind.
The most powerful computer in the world.
My brain gets stronger every
day because I exercise it.
The stronger it gets, the
more money I can make.
He believed that automatically
saying, I can't afford it was
a sign of mental laziness.
Although both dads worked hard, I
noticed that one dad had a habit of
putting his brain to sleep when it
came to money matters, and the other
had a habit of exercising his brain.
The long-term result was that
one dad grew stronger financially
and the other grew weaker.
It is not much different from
a person who goes to the gym
to exercise on a regular basis.
Versus someone who sits on
the couch watching television.
Proper physical exercise increases
your chances for health and proper
mental exercise increases your
chances for wealth, laziness
decreases both health and wealth.
My two dads had opposing attitudes
and thought, one dad thought that
the rich should pay more in taxes and
take care of those less fortunate.
The other said.
Taxes, punish those who produce
and reward those who don't produce.
One.
Dad recommended study hard so you
can find a good company to work for.
The other recommended study hard so
he can find a good company to buy one.
Dad said, the reason I'm not
rich is because I have you kids.
The other said, the reason I must
be rich is because I have you kids.
One dad encouraged talking about money
and business at the dinner table.
The other forbade the subject of
money to be discussed over a meal.
One said, when it comes to money,
play it safe and don't take risks.
The other said, learn to manage risk.
One believed our home is our largest
investment and our greatest asset.
The other believed my house is a
liability, and if your house is your
largest investment, you're in trouble.
Both dads paid their bills on
time, yet one paid his bills first.
While the other paid is Bills last.
Being a product of two strong dads allowed
me the luxury of observing the effects
different thoughts have on one's life.
I noticed that people really do shape
their life through their thoughts.
For example, my poor dad always
said, I'll never be rich, and
that prophecy became reality.
My rich dad, on the other hand,
always refer to himself as rich.
He would say things like, I'm a rich
man, and rich people don't do this.
Even when he was flat broke after a
major financial setback, he continued
to refer to himself as a rich man.
He would cover himself by saying,
there's a difference between
being poor and being broke.
Broke is temporary and poor is eternal.
My poor dad would also say,
I'm not interested in money,
or money, doesn't matter.
My rich dad always said, money is power.
The power of our thoughts may never be
measured or appreciated, but it became
obvious to me as a young boy to be aware
of my thoughts and how I expressed myself.
I noticed that my poor dad was poor,
not because of the amount of money he
earned, which was significant, but because
of his thoughts and his actions as a
young boy having two fathers, I became
acutely aware of being careful which
thoughts I chose to adopt as my own.
Whom should I listen to?
My rich dad or my poor dad?
Although both men had tremendous
respect for education and learning,
they disagreed in what they
thought was important to learn.
One wanted me to study hard,
earn a degree, and get a
good job to work for money.
He wanted me to study to become
a professional, an attorney
or an accountant, or to go to
business school for my MBA.
The other encouraged me to study, to
be rich, to understand how money works.
And learn how to have it work for me.
I don't work for money.
Were the words he would
repeat Over and over.
Money works for me.
At the age of nine, I decided to listen
to and learn from my rich dad about money.
In doing so, I chose not to listen
to my poor dad, even though he was
the one with all the college degrees.
Once I made up my mind whom to listen
to, my education about money began,
my rich dad taught me over a period
of 30 years until I was age 39.
He stopped once he realized that I knew
and fully understood what he had been
trying to drum into my often fixed skull
money is one form of power, but what is
more powerful is financial education.
Money comes and goes, but if
you have the education about how
money works, you gain power over
it and can begin building wealth.
The reason positive thinking alone does
not work is because most people went to
school and never learned how money works.
So they spend their lives working
for money because I was only
nine years old when I started.
The lessons my rich dad taught me
were simple, and when it was all
said and done, there are only six
main lessons repeated over 30 years.
This book is about those six lessons
put as simply as possible, as my rich
dad put forth those lessons to me.
The lessons are not meant to be
answers, but guideposts, guideposts
that will assist you and your
children to grow wealthier.
No matter what happens in a world of
increasing change and uncertainty.